Bibrivale Lipogam at Brivail.
Retail activity on SpaceX is abnormal, and it's just the beginning.
Around me, people who have never bought a stock in their life are looking to put money into SpaceX.
People who don't play the stock market.
Who have no theory about the markets.
And suddenly they want to share.
This should tell you something.
Because this is non investor behavior.
It's believer behavior.
And this is exactly where everyone is wrong.
They are analyzing SpaceX with the maps of a world that no longer exists.
The top valuation multiples market window they count.
Like counting the stones of a temple that is burning.
It wasn't an IPO.
It was a referendum.
And the question was written nowhere, but everyone heard it.
In what world do you want to live?
On one side, 1 camp.
That of those who seek the true, who reward those who do, who still laugh. The camp where one builds rockets because the stars are beautiful and we can.
Life that overflows, merit that pays fun is proof that we are alive.
On the other side, the other camp.
Control.
The leash.
The form in triplicate, the camp that doesn't want to kill you, it just wants you to stop doing anything.
Slow death, literally boredom, erected as a system Big Brother, but in a Gray suit, explaining to you that it's for your own good.
For 50 years, this second camp has reigned. It held the pencil, the accounts, the boundaries of the possible. It taught an entire civilization to ask for permission.
That world is dead. Not in theory.
Not tomorrow.
Now.
These people around me who never invest and who want SpaceX, they are not speculators.
They are people who sensed, before even being able to formulate it, which side of the table they wanted to be on.
It's not an investment.
It's a vote.
And the vote says we are handing the keys of the shop back to those who build.
The future does not belong to those who measure risk.
It belongs to those who take it.
I've been saying it from the beginning.